okay uh we're going to do a
meditation if you feel uh
warm uh you might try putting your hands
on your knees and if you feel Cal try
doing this
thing uh and it helps the meditation
okay watch your
breath
e e
come to the golden
room
e e
look at this
guy e
look at the mountains in the Val
got e
come back to the golden
in e
and ask your teacher to come
and then meditate single pointedly on
their presence
so single
object single thing to think
about that they're sitting in front of
you you feel their presence try
to tie the mind to that presence
and don't be aware of anything
else
e e
like you to
observe when you are
having less than a perfect meditation
I'd like you to observe right now
whether you are tending more towards
dullness or whether you are tending more
to think about something
else
desirable which of the two classical
problems are you having or are you close
to having today this
afternoon e
then after you've identified which
problem you're tending
towards see if you can balance
that consciously within your mind if
your mind is dull not very
bright then see if you can uplift it by
thinking of something
bright luminous something you
enjoy or a little mini meditation on how
lucky you are if your mind is too
agitated and
if it's going to many different objects
outside then see if you can bring it
back down by thinking about loved ones
who have passed
away
e
e e
try to apply the antidote
then come back to this
room slowly open your
eyes uh just out of curiosity how many
people had
dullness and how many people were
thinking about taking off
it's like
50/50 okay I had
both I have to be you know equal and all
this St all
right did the antidote
help I mean for me I just found I
applied the antidote and then the thing
just bounced back like a like one of
those balls attached to a paddle
I did you feel like that did the did the
problem
reoccur no
okay all right we finished the four
uh crucial ideas regarding
Nick Nick I told you oh you're still
there okay I mean you're still not there
uh
then he's going to sort of w he's going
to kind of wrap up okay on that he still
has to get to
the Goa with regard to things we just
been on M okay here we go
uh so try to hold in your mind what it
is the G uh a pen that was a pen from
its own
side and isn't a pen because of how
you've treated others all right try to
hold on to a pen like that you know we
talked
about three way ways of seeing me right
one was the mik way the emptiness way
you looked at me and you said oh that's
just coming from my mind you know
there's nothing out there it's it's
coming from my mind according to how I
treated other and then what was the
second one I was uh shaving in the
mirror John was shaving in the mirror
somebody and
uh and you're just kind of have a
peripheral awareness of you it's not
like you're examining
where you comes from or something you're
just shaving if probably if you thought
about all that stuff you'd cut yourself
and then the third example was where
somebody asked you specifically they got
you in a corner and they said are you
coming from your own side are you coming
from your mind and you said I mean I'm
here it's not coming from my mind I'm
real you know so that's a sort of a
hardcore wrong view a this decided to
have a wrong here okay it can apply to a
pen as well right so try to get the
feeling
of the first one is the pen that's
coming from me and for some reason I got
color now somebody in the class had
bought one of these my
rare Japanese French
pen and they they had a colored one I
always have black ones right so I have I
have not only pen Karma but some kind of
more interesting Karma right okay it
means that our karma for the last five
pages hasn't ripened yet um
so or the second way I can look out is
just it's just a pen okay and then third
way I could look at it is oh it's
definitely coming from its own side
right I can look at it all three
ways anyway he says here hold
that uh
hope that idea of how it appears to you
when you think it's coming from itself
right when you believe that it's coming
this way the third one
right don't lose it try to hold on to
it so in the case of Nick try to focus
on the Nick who didn't deserve to be
blamed okay try to focus on that Nick
and then see how does he relate to his
Parts you know is he his eye is he his
arm or is he somehow the whole thing
okay try to examine those two
possibilities right got
it you had a big
lunch okay count whatever they ate this
time don't let him e it again
uh so you have the Nick who's not there
okay is he his arm and his leg is he his
arm good good
that's good
uh is he is whole is is he everything
together okay good
so examine
it come to the conclusion that he is
neither okay come to the conclusion that
he's in neither place
right for example if you're a Tibetan no
man and you have you you you have a
fence thin pasture uh and it only has
two sides of a hill right so you can't
see the other half when you're on one
half cuz there's a ridge between but
everything's Fen in right so if you uh
and if you lost your cow in the pasture
if someone said to you your cow got out
of the pasture all right your cow is out
of the pasture out of the fence you know
and if in Tibet a cow is a valuable
thing
uh the word for rich is chupo which can
also mean having cows all right so it's
an expensive
thing uh so somebody says your cow got
out of the the fence then you would want
to go and look in the two pastors to see
if he was there or not to check if he
really did get out of the fence
okay you would go to the lowlands you
would go to the highlands you would go
to the
Ridge and then you wouldn't find the cow
cuz the cow got out of the fence it's
not either in the upper pasture or the
lower pasture okay
uh but when you're looking for the cow
isn't it the case that you carry with
you an image in your mind of what the
cow looks like okay you you you get an
image of your in your mind of what the
cow looks like and then you go looking
in the lower pastor and the upper
pastor means woo okay
means uh you have a picture in your mind
of the cow you go to the lower pasture
then you look in the upper pasture and
it's not there and then suddenly there
just whoop in your mind like no cow you
know it's like a feeling right it's
a it's a feeling of uh it's like when
you reach in your hand in your pocket
for the credit card at the restaurant
and you go whoop you know and you're
like you know you're smiling to the
waiter and you're like whoop you know so
uh that's the same feeling there's only
two pastures that Cal can be in upper
lower uh you have a you have a picture
in your mind of where he would be of
what he looks like and then you check in
the two places not there and then you
get this feeling of loss or this feeling
of
uh something not being there okay
so it's the same thing with the Nick who
didn't deserve to get blamed for
stealing the books
okay that make neck is not something you
can see with your eyes Lo
sorry normally you think it would be
someone you could see with your eyes or
hold with your hands okay you could
grasp onto that Nick or you could see
that Nick we s we feel that way
especially when you're the Nick who's
being blamed okay the Nick you who feels
offended the Nick who didn't deserve to
get
blamed
uh that Nick you feel like he should be
there like the cow okay should be
something you could see or deal with sh
sh sho means sh sho means just it just
comes to you like if I hold this up and
say which way is it coming from quickly
and you don't but you didn't come on and
in the first second you you thought it
was coming this way okay that's sh sho
it's just like it's just like an
automatic impression automatic
impression that we usually
have then if you if you know
which Nick you're looking for which Nick
are we looking for the one who didn't
deserve to get blamed okay we look for
him in his arm or he has a sticker on
the real Nick now okay
uh the Nick who doesn't deserve to get
blamed we can look for him in his
fingers his fingernails his his what do
you call it eyebrow hairs and we won't
find him uh we could also look for him
in the sum of his parts and we won't
find them this is where a lot of people
who teach this part of this system get
get lost they they mislead the students
they
they they're saying is
Nick uh his arm and the student says no
and then they say is Nick all all of him
together and then the student says yes
and then this teacher tries to convince
them why they're wrong but they're right
he is all the sum of his part okay we
they make an error at this point because
they're looking for a Nick which really
exists there is a Nick which exists he's
sitting there and he has all his Parts
together that's the conventional nick uh
but there's another Nick the one who
didn't deserve to get blamed you know
that Nick is not there and that Nick is
neither one nor many neither one the
owner of his parts or many the
multiplicity of his parts okay so don't
get don't mislead your students okay
that a lot a lot a lot of people teach
this thing wrong they say can you find
Nick and his is Nick his arm and the
student says no and then they say is
Nick everything together and they say
the student says yes and the student is
right and then the teacher says no
because the teacher thinks they're
looking
for the conventional Nick but you're not
looking for a conventional Nick you're
looking for a Nick that doesn't exist
okay got it it's
okay
okay if it suddenly occurs to
you that the Nick who didn't get deserve
to get
blamed is simply not there okay if you
suddenly have this what do you call
Epiphany that the Nick who didn't
deserve to get blame isn't there
you have come to the middle way you you
are a middle way philosopher okay you
have come to the realization of the
middle way that is the middle way you
have um means you have found the view of
the middle way and it's not so difficult
right it's not such a big deal it's
easier to use a
person and it's easier to say just
anybody who didn't deserve anything that
happened to them that's easy
because that person doesn't exist
nowhere and it never did and that's a
good example because that's the person
you want to defend when someone accuses
you you know the person the the Brandy
who didn't deserve to be blam right uh
if if suddenly she doesn't exist then
all your hard work of protecting
yourself interest and and you know
watching out for number one they can all
be let go
because that person doesn't exist
there's no need to defend a person who's
not there
okay do you need to defend the person
who is blamed
properly no I mean there's a there's a
me who was blamed because of my past
seed because I blame people in the past
do you need to defend that
person it's useless there's no point to
it okay they are going to be blamed as
much as they blamed others and it will
wear out and then they won't be blamed
anymore so there's no need to defend
them you can't defend them there you
cannot stop the ripening of their karma
they they will be blamed okay who me
okay so then there's no point to
defending them and you can't def who are
you going to defend them
from you
all right the only person left to defend
them from is
yourself and there nobody likes to do
that so then so you can just drop the
defending okay all
right this is really beautiful okay this
is really
beautiful uh someone who is spiritually
has a high I call High spiritual IQ okay
they call it uh w n okay it means sharp
faculties but what it means is you have
a high spiritual IQ because you've been
a nice person for couple life times or
more okay and you have a high
sensitivity to spiritual things you are
attracted to those ideas they are
interesting to you uh you follow them
you read about them you always have
since you're in high school
uh that's a wongon that's a high
spiritual IQ okay those kinds of people
when they get into a class like this and
they get a good explanation about the
Nick who who's not there the niku didn't
deserve to be blamed right and then
suddenly they have some kind of
a they have some kind of a I don't
know something happens to them we see it
on the DCI tours all the time we go to a
place maybe a thousand Chinese people
show up they are hardcore business
people they're not interested in
spiritual things then you explain the
pen thing and you explain the seed thing
and like 45 minutes into the talk this
light lights up in their eyes and they
and they're like wow that explains
everything in my life that explains
everything I ever thought in my life you
know and they they just get this light
in their eyes and then you got them you
know then the hard thing is to keep them
doing whatever business they were
doing uh because they want to quit and
uh become a DCI teacher uh really it's a
big problem we've ruined a lot of
businesses with our business
seminars
uh but this light lights up in their
eyes and they every every intelligent
person can get it you know you you
explain it slowly this thing and then
you get into into the emptiness and and
then suddenly this this light and they
feel like they feel like I just got a
precious thing you know like it's like
somebody gave you a Mercedes or you know
or someone in
uh where was
it Elon somebody in Elon some movie star
lady came up and took a ring off and
like this huge diamond ring you know I'm
like no no no I don't take you know and
then she said no no you you take it and
then we had this big fight at her house
at her yoga studio and uh but then you
know she she I felt like she would be
offended I felt like she would get angry
and then it would be a bad prise I said
okay I'll take it and we PID somebody's
airfare wom it
um but as if you had just been given
something very precious okay someone who
really understands life if someone gives
them a clear explanation of what the
hell's been going on all this time you
know and what you can do about it then
they're
like wow thanks you know like wow you
really gave me something okay okay W to
okay what's W the ones without spiritual
IQ okay the eaters and TV Watchers
somebody who doesn't
have
spiritual IQ High spiritual I will feel
as the opposite as if they had lost
something
precious and they will be
afraid okay like okay like they'll
suddenly say oh where am I where's M you
know you say there's no mic check your
parts check your hole there's no Nick
uh a person with a high aptitude will
feel the sense of relief now I now the
world makes sense and a person without a
high attitude will say oh my God there's
no me you know where am I and they will
feel like they lost the diamond
ring okay they have the opposite effect
on them okay
J and then Kim Min is interesting what's
Kim Min do
in it's a joke okay it's an India joke
sorry uh in India if the driver if the
car sort of Putters out and the driver
comes around to your side and says no
problem sir then you know you're going
to have to spend the night on the road
somewhere you know no problem
means car so K do means no problem no
problem sir uh kin means uh it's
interesting P says if a
person rather than feeling they had just
won the lottery feels like their mother
just
died okay then he
says said that's not a problem because
they got it to some extent they got it
or else they wouldn't have felt some
kind of fear if they didn't feel like
Nick was gone they wouldn't be concerned
so he's like don't sweat you know they
freak out a little bit no problem okay
they it's cuz they got it partly so at
least they got it partly they at least
they feel something's gone that's good
all
right
J J Kaa in the towards the end of his
life uh his disciples started to really
get into uh
Monastery founding
mode like they founded gundan Sarah de
with a combined
monastic enrollment of like 20,000 monks
you know like it was I mean after so I
mean these were big things this is like
Harvard DL prin or something his
students in a few years time towards the
end of his life they just really went
wild and started founding major
institutions okay and he actually taught
at Sarah when it was just a cow pasture
all right uh you know later it became
10,000 monks but he taught there when
they were just opening it okay like it
was just a square mile in Glendale
Arizona empty lot okay uh or okay not a
square mile don't freak out Jamie all
right
uh half a square miles okay thought way
J J uh so he did teach at Sarah and it
was probably a chair in the middle of a
field okay uh
dingu and then he taught emptiness
sitting there
where in a field in the opening days of
Sarah okay and uh T nup then there was a
a a student named j shab s okay
there's a very special student sh sing
he uh so just a couple words like a few
days later he was sitting there it was
that Sarah I think in the field that
Sarah and then SOA said you know we
really need it these all these
monasteries are very good but we need a
a yoga
Monastery you know we need a a mon we
need a special Monastery for the secret
teachings the yoga inner and outer yoga
we need a and then everybody was like
yeah you know all these high disciples
were like like yeah we really yeah
that's
true and uh and then shed up S it he was
back in the back he was not very he was
not famous disciple he wasn't like G of
j k j something and then he saw he was
embarrassed that all the number one
disciples didn't offer to build a yoga
Monastery so he he you know he said I'll
do it
you know it's very
beautiful and then he found
a
t which is where art teacher comes from
okay sh anyway he was teaching uh jenta
was teaching emptiness sherab seni was
sitting in the back and then suddenly
sharabi
goes you know and he felt like he had
lost himself and he was hanging on to
his to his top you know he was like he
was like trying to make sure he was
still there you know like some cop is
talking and S is going
like you know and
okay then Jay Jay Ken J Kaa realized
what was going on with him and then gay
gay means that he was like
big smile big he was really happy okay
and
then oh the monk from narang has been
able to establish the existence of
deceptive
reality I mean he's like n tongue is
just like Kansas okay and uh he said oh
the boy from Kansas had a had a bit of a
realization just
now okay cuz he was like
[Laughter]
okay all
right very famous Lama in our
tant and there's also this story that uh
muchu Quicksilver Lama Quicksilver gave
a particularly compelling presentation
of emptiness and then half the students
freaked out they just freaked out like
they couldn't find
themselves
okay if if the you tends to melt
into if you lose the youu okay if the if
it goes into it's called Tong Cham Tong
Cham means sheer sheer
voidness okay if you melt into sheer
voidness and then you think to yourself
oh that's emptiness or you think to
yourself I've realized emptiness okay he
says uh L
sh check what comes to mind okay check
what comes to your mind you you feel
like everything went into the sheer void
then he says check what comes to mind if
what comes to
mind is that one thing is not another
thing my okay if what comes to mind is
that one thing is not another
thing or if what comes to mind is a
positive
thing then you got it
wrong okay so there's there's three
choices here okay one is called me one
is called m one is called dupa and I
would have you repeat it but you can't
so just do it in your mind May me and
dupa okay dupa is easy okay dupa is like
dupa means a positive thing okay for
example some people come out of they
come home after they come back after a
big teaching on emptiness and they say I
saw emptiness and you say well what was
it like and they say it's kind of a blue
head you know and it's just kind of an
aura over everything blue aura over
everything and that's already wrong
because blue is a positive thing see
it's not the absence of something it's
very important to understand that
emptiness is an absence of something so
if somebody says oh I saw emptiness and
you say what's it look like and they say
it's kind of foggy but it has a silver
color then you already know that that
they're wrong okay my indox a little
harder Mok
means
uh it's not the Nick you thought it was
it's a different Nick something like
that okay it's the Nick that really does
exist is different from the Nick who was
wrongly blamed
okay the Nick who really does exist uh
is different from the Nick who was
wrongly blame
but that doesn't make it emptiness just
to be something else Emptiness is
neither
is nor is Emptiness is something else
emptiness can only ever be it's not
there it has to be the full thing it's
not there inet there's two different
verbs it's one verb for is and there's a
different verb for is there he is
Reeses is not here today two different
things
okay he is not R is a may God it's a
it's a denial of something okay but
retesh is not here is in absence of
something okay and that's different so
if the idea you have of emptiness is
simply that something is not something
else or something positive you're on the
wrong track if you have a sense of
something missing something gone missing
Earl Bernie it must be something
Vancouver thing uh he'll always say Gua
the shovels have gone missing you know
and uh it means they're not there then
that's empty that's that's a candidate
for emptiness that's a mega that's an
absence of something okay so he's saying
here if if it if you have some kind of
thing come up in your mind that's either
positive or simply not something else J
M mad Jason mad means don't don't go for
that don't go for that one that one's
wrong
okay this is very very
famous and very very uh much a part of
our Ted practice bini practice okay uh
in the bini practice there are four
qualities of emptiness okay what was
that do you remember
that I am okay that's a different story
that's a whole different thing but two
of them come here two of them come here
okay and it's important
okay in the act of misunderstanding Nick
there's a partnership between two two
bad things okay two bad things Okay can
take up two bad guys shaking hands you
know let's kill the president you know
and they're like and make a deal one guy
will do one thing and one guy will do
the other thing if you saw salt
okay uh or Angela Julie okay you you the
two two guys have to be collaborating
okay for for us to really have ignorance
a Vidya depends on two two separate
components there has to be a strategic
cooperation
between two different components to have
a really good inance okay one uh Nick
has to appear from
it to you as if he were coming from his
own side if you want an enhancement of
that feeling uh wait until somebody
blames you okay and you'll have an
enhanced feeling of it I was you know I
was half asleep this morning I was
thinking about you guys and I was
thinking that when I was thinking about
gaka I some realization I had about gaka
at some point in my
life if you're feeling
unhappy if you're feeling depressed if
you're feeling anxious if you're feeling
angry about something or sad about
something or or wronged by
somebody that's a barometer that you are
dealing in gas okay if if you
anytime you're unhappy you are dealing
with a gaka so if you're not quite sure
what the gaka is just wait till you're
unhappy and you must there must be a
gacha in there somewhere if you're
unhappy it's it's it's a keba it must be
okay anyone who's unhappy at any given
moment is dealing a gaka there's
somewhere there there's a gaka usually
it's me you know is there a me yes is
there and me who got wrongly blamed no
okay but when you feel
unhappy uh you can just assume there's a
go there then go looking for it okay try
to find it anytime you don't
feel what do you call it joyful there's
probably a GCKA around
somewhere messing you up okay so anyway
here two two things needed for a good
ignorance for a really
sweet uh a viid you you need two
different things going on
one there has to be a nick uh appearing
to me uh I'm Nick okay there has to be a
Nick appearing to me who was wrongly
blend okay there has to be some kind of
unreal appearance coming at me all right
there has to be an unreal thing coming
at me niku is wrongly blend okay unreal
something has to be coming at me which
is wrong
okay and then you can guess the second
half what's the second
half I have to believe in
it okay I have to buy into
right
okay so here's the two
in for for for occasion of wisdom for
wisdom you need the opposite okay you
have to be looking at
Nick and then like dividing water from
milk skillfully you have to pick out the
Nick who's not there and see that it
never was there what appears to you was
never there okay you have to cancel
what's appearing to
you then from from from your wisdom side
then your wisdom has to say that that
that doesn't exist that that's the
emptiness of the Nick I thought was
there before for okay an act of wisdom
also requires two things going
on emptiness emptiness appearing to the
wisdom and wisdom interpreting it as
emptiness okay all right two
things you must have a state of
certainty which has two those two
characteristics
it things are appearing as though there
were emptiness to it and it is taking
them as empty okay all
right don't forget
it hold
it and try to stay there stay in that
okay so someday in your experience you
know probably when someone hurts you
really bad okay uh someone really hurts
you and then this big me will come up
you know this me who didn't deserve to
be hurt you know we can sit here all day
and talk about deserving what comes to
us then when you go outside and someone
says you know the smallest thing to you
and then you know the the mic who's not
real pops up you know like I didn't do
that I don't know why you're saying that
it was a perfectly good class you know
uh you know what I mean don't it just
you get just got out of the class
explaining why you deserve everything
and someone criticized your class and
you're like you know and then that's the
that's the mic that doesn't exist
okay hold
it so means if you start to lose
it like you catch the M you know you you
taught this class for 10 days you went
outside somebody filled out an
evaluation for him he said I had one in
Singapore was it no Shanghai we spoke to
the entrepreneurs organization which is
the baby YPO guys and uh that the guy it
was a really you know high class group
and and all these great business owners
and then the Jules guy Jules his name he
ran up to me afterwards he says I got
you evaluation forms in EO you have to
fill out evation forms before you go
home because they gave you a free dinner
and you have to you have to write how
youd like to talk and he said look at
this 10 10 10 10 10 and then he goes
look at this
one and I'm like what he says by the way
that's the highest rain we ever had in a
talk and I'm like sure and then
uh then he says then he says but look at
this last one you know and it says
000000 and it says this guy must be on
drugs
[Laughter]
so then you get this thing you know you
you just finished telling the EO how
everything's coming from yourself and
then you're like how could he say that
you you
know so then when the when that comes up
you got to be waiting for that you got
to be waiting for someone to give you a
good insult so keep your eyes open uh
and then it comes up and then he says
grab it just hold it you know grab that
grab that mic grab that mic don't let
him go hold on to him observe him you
know look there's the mic that doesn't
exist I got a gotcha
gotcha some people said my my students
in New York used to call it
gacha uh because you can grab the gcha
and you can say okay I got you know then
you MMA him right was it
MMA he showed me 5 minutes of MMA you
don't want to see it this is like
martial arts plus boxing no
rules but then you got to do it to the
gck
CH this guy was straggling a guy and
just punching me in the head over and
over and over and there's no rules you
can just do that you know and and then
you got to do that to the gck job
okay you basically you get in a grip
like this and you just punch
him and uh
yeah um so when you catch a gaka hold
on don't let your recognition of who he
is fail Don't Let It Fade hold it hold
that insult you know hold that feeling
me Michael R you know and
then if it starts to fade okay if the
gcha starts to slip out of your hands
gcha is like a greased Pig right the
okay he's actually talking about inner
meditation okay try to in a meditation
to bring up a gaka and try to hold it
it's not difficult because most of us
spend most of our meditation time
thinking about the wrongs that people
have done us okay so you don't have to
get out of your
meditation you don't have to come out in
the meditation
try
to don't don't don't stir yourself from
your meditation hold the
Gat as strongly as you can and then go
through the reasons why he can't be
there review the reasons why he can't be
there you know has Michael Roach never
accused someone else of being on drugs
like so philosophically incoherent that
they're on drugs you know I mean has he
never said anything like that uh okay
because if he hasn't then it's
undeserved if he has then it's totally
deserved it's expected it's
required okay can either mean into that
to
me or it can
mean meditation
meditational intensity so he's saying
turn your Nar to this gaka turn your to
this gaka you're like hey I've been
looking for you it's so cool that you
showed up you know and you're so strong
and bright right now you know you're so
like outstanding right now you're so
like obvious to me right at this moment
standing there in Shanghai in that
restaurant you know with that little
stun silence you know and and you're
like yeah I've been waiting for you you
know and then feel some pleasure that
that you got him you know you've been
waiting a long time to catch an extreme
case of an EXT extreme case of gcha and
now you got a now you got it and
appreciate it and has some you're like
feel happy that you got
her and go into
which
is right
there sorry right there go into say
chick on it go into say on that gaka get
to know the gaka there all these subtle
half invisible things running around in
your mind right now you know how to
identify the part of your mind which
raises the alarm when your
meditation failing you've also learned
you've met face to face the part of your
mind which brings your mind back
and you've even met the meditational
contentment and depth which is n okay
now get to know gaka in meditation get
to know
gaka in the the process of meditation is
learning to identify within your own
mind all these very very subtle
mechanisms of your mind that you were
just unaware of but we're going on all
along it's very very beautiful okay get
to know your mind the way you would get
to know the people in a room you know
put little uh what do you call name tags
on on different parts of your mind oh
that's that's n you know wow I've been
looking for you that's gcha that's Juma
that oh that's
agitation you know instead of instead of
following the thought about lunch You
observe the thought about lunch and you
say ah that you're on the poster I saw
you on the post you you're like the
rabbit or the monkey or something you
know I saw you you know and then like
learn to
identify the the the different workings
of your mind and then you then you
really know something you know people
like to know foreign language or the
Latin names for parts of your body or
but this is so much cooler you know I
know oh you're our you know hi
get to know all the subtle pieces in
your mind
okay so
then there's a meditation on emptiness
there's a there's a point in your
meditations on emptiness that we call
Nam
okay Nam means space okay
there's a debate in Abid Dharma which
you should be aware
of there's a conventional Numa and
there's the real nka
okay nka can mean Sky Akasha right it
can mean Sky we named him aash we made
him a monk we Nam him aash which is the
Sanskrit for Sky okay so
sky right can be a the blue thing is is
is a sky but that's not the pH opical
meaning of space okay uh the
philosophical meaning of namka or
Akash is the absence of anything is
space okay if you think about it
carefully you can say place okay
Place uh I'll give you an
example uh
these are opening lines of the okay and
they talk about space it's talking about
space okay it's very easy to find things
which are constantly changing because
everything around you is is
changing
okay but it's but it's rather difficult
to to to find something which is
unchanging but which still exists okay
all right and there's only a few
in the Abid there's only three so one of
them is space okay why what does that
mean okay here's a mint that somebody
gave me or rat poison I don't know um I
think it's a mint okay somebody gave me
a
Min somebody gave me a
Min okay uh it's occupying a certain
position in space right uh the mint is
occupying a certain position in
space I can remove the mint from that
space I I always when I give this
teaching I always think of going on an
airplane and there's a little uh piece
of plastic on the seat that says
ocupado okay so this is
acup that that position in space and I'm
not talking in my hand I'm talking in
the universe you know certain
coordinates relative to Sirus Sirus and
and Alpha Omega you know you could
pinpoint this space this place in space
between all the
Stars this has a place there's a
coordinate which describes where this
mint is in in space Okay then if you
move
it what happens to the
space it becomes unocup this
occup uh
[Music]
mayor these are the opening lines
up Donkey
hot uh so that's
AAP you check it uh uh so I'm I'm
showing off the Spanish so anyway Des
means uh it's not occupied anymore but
did it change see the place didn't
change the space didn't change okay
that's what they mean when they say
empty space okay and that's a very
profound thing because Emptiness is very
similar okay it's one of the most
similar things to emptiness right empty
space or place empty space is one of the
most similar things to emptiness okay
why uh it's defined by a lack
of uh
obuity I
construction which all that means is
that the space is there whether it's
occupied or not okay the space is always
there the space is always available it
can be occupied or not if it were not
available even when it was occupied it
would spit out the mint and it would fly
back into my hand you see what I mean
there there is empty space there and it
is available or else the Min couldn't be
there even when the mint's there there's
available space because it it may be
occupied but it's still there okay
so emptiness is similar okay you got to
get used
to uh when you see emptiness
directly it will be an experience of a
higher reality of a reality you were
never aware of okay it's a direct
experience of a higher reality almost
what do you call it Indescribable the
actual experience is
Indescribable but
uh it's like space it's called it's
called like
space because there's an overwhelming
feeling of nothing there okay something
is absent okay it's an absence of
something okay
you and there's no other feeling like
that you can't describe it it's just a
total a sheer absence of something okay
and it's
higher and and all things exist within
it and without it nothing could exist
see so you come to the base reality of
all things when you reach emptiness
without it nothing could exist
okay so it's a it's a higher it's a
higher level of reality
okay uh
so anyway that's called that's called
space likee
meditation this was a little bit
difficult for me when I read it okay
this this part was a little difficult
for me he said at that point meaning
when you're when you're starting to feel
that absence of Nick of the Nick who was
wrongly blamed when you find that
absence okay they
say uh there's a side effect Shuki means
there's a side effect okay uh
you you establish that the mic you
thought was there is not there and then
that creates another impression in in
deep in meditation that creates another
impression okay what's
that when you're in a deep meditation
upon the absence of the Nick who was
ever who was never there it's rather
difficult to find the Nick who is
there okay it's not that he doesn't
exist it's not that he's a Gaga it's
just that you're so engrossed in the
absence of the one nck that you kind of
lose the other one for a while all right
in the actual direct perception of
emptiness you
can't perceive anything which is not the
absence of Nick the wrong Nick so you
can't perceive yourself you can't
perceive the meditation you can't
perceive time going by you can't be
aware of any other thing which is not
the absence of the Nick who is never
there okay it's just not possible so so
Pabon is describing a a deep state of
meditation you are close or you are or
you are seeing emptiness directly and
then you will lose ni you will lose the
real n because he's not emptiness and
you are single pointed on emptiness okay
if you're single pointed an emptiness
and anything is not
emptiness you can't see it okay it's
like if you're really single pointed on
the golden room you cannot be aware of
this room it's not possible if you're
really single pointed on your teacher's
face you can't see their
chest okay it's not possible if you have
real meditation real real
meditation then you can't perceive
anything else because real meditation
means aagra single point okay so when
you have finally
located the absence of the Nick that was
never there you the Nick who is there
might slip away for a while he says
don't freak out don't worry about it
okay means talk means uh ungrounded fear
all right you don't have to have an
ungrounded fear that uh you are falling
into what we call Cheta Cheta means
nihilism okay it's the Buddhist word for
nihilism what is
nihilism it means oh uh the Nick I
thought was there is not there so
nothing exists there is no Nick
someone gives you a good teaching about
how the Nick you thought was there is
not there and then you decide there's no
Nick at all you know okay you go too far
you cancel everything that's called
CH you don't have to worry that you're
folling into nihilism if you lose the me
who's really there while you're focusing
on the fact that the me who was never
there is not
there okay you don't have to should I
say it
you don't have to worry that you are
following falling into a nihilistic view
which holds that nothing exists if you
lose the Nick who does exist while
you're focusing on the absence of the
Nick who couldn't have been there all
right
okay means don't exhaust yourself in a
fruitless effort that's me okay what try
to find the Nick who is there cuz that's
not the point at that time just rest in
the absence of the Nick who couldn't
have been there and don't don't go
freaking out and looking to find the
Nick who is there cuz he's going to sit
there he's there don't worry he's
meditating okay you don't have to worry
that you're going to lose that nck okay
don't he says don't Tu don't Tucker
yourself out me go by looking for him at
the wrong moment okay because while
you're focusing on the absence of the
Nick who couldn't have been there you
can let the other Nick go for a while
he'll come back when you stop meditating
okay okay
so uh what's the
time we still in a few minutes
right oh wait
not what time is I supposed to
stop 3:30 right is it okay if we go a
little bit more I know it's warm in here
and I know you're tired
uh but but we still have to trck through
this we have to keep on schedule for the
10year
plan okay I studied Russian in college
and I hated it uh and
uh at the time it was the Soviet Union
so the only literature coming out of the
Soviet Union was 10-year plans and
five-year plans
and heroes of Soviet labor stories she
grew 38 chickens in a month
you know they banned all the other stuff
dooski tolto
anyway we have a 10-year plan and if I
don't finish uh if I don't finish a
certain amount in this Retreat we're
going to get behind and then we'll be
getting into 2024 something okay here we
go it'll come
fast diamond mountain we I said seven
years and everybody's like oh that a
long
time it's finished
okay he has
finished a very very general
description which was supposed to end in
a dramatic moment when we were seeing
emptiness directly
okay that experience
uh takes about 20 minutes okay and
uh it takes billions of lifetimes to get
there okay it takes billions of
lifetimes to get to that 20 minutes
takes billions of
lifetimes and then due to many factors
but most importantly your study of your
study of these things then you go into
the direct perception of
emptiness and it's a just a simple
absence of who you thought you were it's
just the simple absence of who you
thought you were and then you stay there
and you don't know how long because you
can't be aware of
time uh when you come down and you look
at the what the clock you
can you know how long you were in but
you didn't know it when you were in and
you're not even aware of yourself and
also there's no time in there to go hey
I did
it okay like afterwards you're like hey
I did it you know after all these years
uh but while you're in it you can't even
think about me you lose the conventional
Nick right uh
then you come we'll talk more about that
I think tomorrow okay evening is the
best time to talk about that
uh because evening is the time for
wisdom and uh knowledge and emptiness
and it's the woman's time in the
scriptures considered the woman's time
and that's considered the best time to
talk about something like the direct
perception but when you come down out of
the direct perception of is there's a
thing called jop okay J say jop in your
head okay and then you at that point you
have what we call J
say okay so he's going on to explain jop
okay he's moving on to jop jop if you
saw emptiness in let's say 10:00 in the
morning jop would pretty much last till
midnight okay jop yes would last till
about
midnight and there's a lot of cool stuff
that happens to you during that time
because of the karma you collected by
seeing something which could liberate
every being on every planet of the
universe okay so that's a pretty good
karma then you have weird things
happening to you for 24 hours okay for
the
next what 14 15 hours you have all these
weird things happening to you because
your karma is extraordinary so you can
read other people's minds and you can
see 500 years into the future things
like that okay um you have bodh you see
the faces of every living
creature in all Worlds at the same
time but there's a another important
thing happens to you the moment you come
out of your first experience of the
direct perception emptiness you say to
yourself G
Wall-E uh
or whatever the Chinese is I don't know
uh but you could say uh but you say uh
what is Fantastico what do you say in
Spanish I don't know you but anyway it's
like it's like
wow that's the first time I ever saw
anything
correctly in my life okay my whole
life even those Impressions fleeting
Impressions that took a second or two
seconds they were all mistaken okay I
was grossly mistaken in every perception
I ever had in my whole life up to now up
till today everything I ever thought was
wrong okay and the way things appeared
to me was
deceiving and I was fooled by everything
in my whole life I was fooled by
everything colors
shapes presidents
airplanes
thoughts Impressions emotions Partners I
was everything was wrong everything I
saw
wrong
uh but now I've seen now I've had a now
I've seen how things really are but then
you come down you see you can't sustain
the perception you don't have the karma
to sustain the perception you come down
and the old perception reasserts
itself okay the old impression reasserts
itself you start seeing things very
fundamentally as coming from their own
side
even while I'm explaining that it's not
coming from its own side you are holding
that it's coming from its own side even
while I'm explaining it and my words you
are taking as coming from their own side
and me you're taking as coming from
their own side okay you are making the
mistake as we all agree that we've
understand the mistake uh you are still
making it okay the the interesting thing
is when you come out of the direct
perception
emptiness that mistake reasserts itself
but you know you're wrong okay you know
you're are wrong after that if someone
asked you is what you're seeing real
you'll say no or at least it's not the
way I thought it that I think it is well
how is it really I don't know I can't
see that quite yet you see I know it's
wrong but I can't do anything I like to
think of uh what was the guy's name who
went looking for the golden
flee
uh is it
Jason
yeah uh where is Jason yeah Jason's back
there uh
I think it's Jason I don't remember
exactly but they go by the land of the
sirens there's a place called the sirens
the sirens are these uh very beautiful
women who sing a very beautiful song and
then the sailors get excited and they
want to go meet the ladies and they head
their ship in towards that Village on
the side of the water and there's Jagged
reefs there and they always crash their
bone and they all die and then the oh no
the sirens take them prisoner or
something and they become slays of the
sirens I forget at least they lose all
their
stuff uh and usually they're alive okay
so Jason knows about the
sirens uh and he and he does this clever
thing like he's he's roll around to get
the fleece and he's got all these guys
rowing the boat so he says we're going
we're about to hit the land of the
sirens so here's wax he gives everybody
beeswax and he says Jam this into your
ear so you can't hear the sence and then
he says before you do that tie me to the
Mast and uh don't put any wax in my ears
and
then and you know and then I'm going to
be crazy for a while and I'm going to be
begging you to release me but don't
don't do it okay it's very cute you know
it's like I'm in in 20 minutes I'm going
to be crazy
in an hour after that I'll be myself
again but between the 20 minutes and the
hour whatever I do I say just ignore it
and tie me to the mask and don't obey my
instructions for an hour you know and
they tie him to the mask and then he
hears the sirens and then he goes wild
like he's trying to we gotta go you know
we gotta go and they all say yeah
yeah
uh that's the closest way that I can uh
relate the feeling of uh what it is to
come out of emptiness and then
understand that you're crazy you know to
still know you're to still to know that
you're
wrong and not be able to stop it you see
so much later when you reach Boda level
number eight when you reach
nirvana you're able to stop the
appearance of things the wrong way but
up till that time you're like Jason
everything is calling you and you
believe it and you know you're wrong
it's very interesting it's a
schizophrenic state of being and and
it's called Gumble Gumble
means the illusory stages why things
appear to you to be coming from their
own side and for the first time you can
appreciate it fully but you cannot stop
it you can't stop things looking to you
the wrong way but you know you're wrong
okay so it's a very weird G that's real
gab that's real jetto jto means the
period after you see emptiness directly
the gimu lasts for the rest of your life
until you reach nirvana you know you
walk around saying everything looks a
certain way but I know it's wrong you
know and I can't stop seeing it that way
got it you know you're seeing it wrong
and you can't stop it so it's a it's
called the stages of Illusion
okay after you come out of that
meditation
uh now he's talking about sort of a
conventional meditation on the Nick
who's not there so you chose to take as
your meditation object the Nick who was
not there and you medit you had a good
meditation on the Nick who was not there
right and you did a pretty good job of
cancelling the Nick who couldn't have
been there all right then you come out
of the meditation then he says sh
do now now there's sort of a what do you
call
it what do you call it there's something
left to clean
up I guess you call it
that anyway there's something left to do
there's still the big job was done and
now there's uh that's created a smaller
job okay what's the smaller job
do you have to examine how much Nick is
M okay you went into a good
meditation uh you met the Nick who was
not
there which is the Nick who was wrongly
blamed okay you got a good clear picture
of him he's Mr G gcha and you gacha the
gcha you got him you mm what is it MMA
is it you MMA him for a while and then
he kind of went away okay the Nick who
was never
there how do you know he's gone away you
don't feel angry anymore how do you know
he's still there you are in any way
unhappy okay if if if throughout your
day for even 30 seconds you are unhappy
you are directly dealing with a gaka you
are there's something going on with a
gaka there's no unhappiness in the world
which is not directly related to
misperceiving yourself
it's not possible to be unhappy unless
you are misperceiving the reality around
you okay it's a it's a measure of of
your understanding okay because if you
really understand you cannot be unhappy
it's not possible it's really weird
right but I guess that's the
point what's left after you MMA the the
Nick who was never there okay you come
out of your meditation you say well how
much Nick is there you know how much
real Nick is there
left okay very very important
mingam mingam means
uh Nam Matra right namama Matra means uh
no more than a than
a the text says and the tradition is to
say Ming only a name nothing left but a
name but it's wrong it's misleading okay
and and if you read this text carefully
you find the what name refers to in this
context which is the picture of Nick
coming out of your head due to the
amount of kindness you showed others in
the
past the picture of Mike or Nick coming
out of your
head uh due to the amount of kindness or
you have or haven't shown to others in
the past that's all that's left of me
after you IM MMA what does MMA stand for
you can't tell me it's some kind of
mixed martial arts yeah you can kick you
can bite you can punch you can you know
everything okay you can't bite all right
I knew that
uh but
anyway
uh what's left after you get finished
MMA the Nick who was never there is the
Nick
who's who's who's flowing from the seeds
in your mind that you planted by being
good or not to others that's the only
Nick okay M only name but it means only
the picture coming out of your mind
that's all the Nick there ever really
was that's the only Nick there ever
really was okay the Nick that was
flowing out of your mind from seeds you
collected by hurting or helping other
people okay that's the only Nick there
when you get finished punching out the
gaka Nick the only Nick left is the one
that's flowing out of your mind from
your own seats
okay this uh Nick who's left over after
we punched out the the Nick who was
never there how we punch a Nick who was
never there I don't know but we'll talk
about that
the one that's left
over this now he's shifting to a whole
new important subject okay whole new
important
subject that Nick can do everything and
there's no problem with that that Nick
can hurt people that Nick can be nice to
people that Nick can keep his vows that
Nick can break his vows that Nick can
collect Good Karma that Nick can collect
Bad Karma okay that Nick exists and that
Nick can do stuff
and that's a big deal you're supposed to
go wow you know and a loser in Nick can
do everything you see Dr the only Nick
who can do everything the Nick who's
flowing from your own
seeds that Nick can do all the stuff you
that that you used to think the other
Nick was doing that Nick can do
everything no problem
okay last chapter
yra uh he can collect white Karma he can
collect black Karma he can collect
neutral uh kak Noah and he can undergo
their respective
consequences no problem that Nick who's
only flowing from Nick's seeds he can he
can commit Karma and he can experience
the consequences of the
Karm you
must come to
a strong grasp of this of this that the
illusory Nick can do
everything
okay is the bumper on a taxi speeding
down a street in New York City coming
from your
mind yes can it still break your
leg
definitely you know and will you still
have to pay the bill that you get from
the hospital
yes all because of a a bumper who's
coming from your mind it's almost not
fair
okay now they get into the example of a
a magician okay
uh I'll just finish that and then we'll
stop
they talk a lot in the ancient books
about the concept of a magic show okay
and if you've ever been to one in a
village in India it's really fun so you
know a a
walking mendicant magician Yogi comes
walks into town it's all exciting and
the the first people to detect him are
the little kids and they rush out of
this they rush out of the street and
they say oh a magician is here
you know and then the elders are a
little bit they just put up with it you
know and then first thing he does he
goes to the chai shop and Demands a free
chai free teeth and he gets
one uh and you know he gets a free snack
and then by that time a big crowd of
kids has come and then the older kids
come and then their parents come and
then pretty soon all you can see is this
massive people you can't see the
magician in the middle uh but you know
magician's there if you see a mass of
people so you kind of like
you work your way towards the front you
know and then uh you get to where the
magician is and then um he takes it's
called a de he takes a what do you call
a token he takes a token sometimes it's
wood sometimes it's Stone and he does a
mantra this is the old meaning of Mantra
it's magic you know he and he does a
mantra and he blows it on and then
suddenly goes like this and there's a
cow and you really see a cow everybody
see everybody backs up if you're in the
front you get squashed you know like
everybody backs up and there's this big
cow there with horns you know and
everybody's like oh and
then and then it's just a stick he has
this way it's beautiful it's very
amazing I don't know exactly it must be
a man or something I don't know but it
looks like a real cow and you're afraid
you like you back up and it's this big
Longhorn cow you know and you think
always going to gore me you
know what does the magician say
he just sees a stick okay uh he's immune
to the Mantra and there's some kind of
powder maybe it's a hallucina I don't
know he throws some kind of powder no
it's a mantra and some powder and then
and then everybody sees a cow except the
magician okay he just sees a
stick even though sorry I'm sorry I blew
it he also sees a c because he he the
powder touches him and the Mantra also
affects him but
what he's not afraid of it cuz he knows
it's not real he knows it's not he knows
if he reached out he could put his hand
through the cow nobody else knows that I
mean they kind of know it but they're
all afraid but the the magician still
sees the cow but they know it's not real
okay they see the illusion they see
through the illusion but they still see
the cow that's similar to a person who
just came out of the direct perception
of emptiness they still see things the
wrong way but they know it's wrong they
they know it's not really that way okay
all right we'll stop there